[Music]
okay so we're speaking here with Bonita
Roy and Jonathan Rosen and we're talking
about bonitas
new let's say it seems like a manifesto
to me on some level even though that's a
rather dramatic way of putting it
but we are living in dramatic times and
the article for emerge is called Corona
19 a tale of two systems bonita you
wrote this article proposing that we you
had six steps towards creating a new
prospect kind of prosperity okay in
light of the crisis that that's going on
and systems collapse and what can can
sort of come next and one of them was
expand our political economic
imagination design a global commons and
service to life experience the deeper
sources of connection expand circles of
trust and concern reinvent education for
the future and pivot to digital
naturalism so that's a lot of stuff and
and you also divide you sort of you're
you're dividing the current systems of
the world into two systems two worlds so
in a way we're living in two worlds and
and one world is sort of doomed and the
other world has some kind of possibility
so is that enough for you to work in may
kind of introduce your vision bonita
yeah I think we should back up and yeah
so that was interesting so I think that
reflected like how the article might
impacted you but I want I want to start
with something Jonathan said when he
asked me to make a contribution on
corona and I think you said it like it's
a lot of stuff and Jonathan said why is
this list important like it you know
there's all kinds of less people put up
and and I really appreciated that
feedback because I feel the same way
like why these five things why not those
five things so why these and so maybe we
can backtrack and kind of frame it in
Jonathan was looking at the drafts in
the process and his invitation yeah so
maybe we can we can start start with
that I'll just briefly speak to that so
I mean I run a charity in London called
perspectiva and and we was co-founded
the Thomas Bjorkman who some of your
viewers will know and we you know three
or four years ago began to realize that
if you want understand complex systems
we need to also bring in the soul
somehow and a part of the problem with a
lot of thinking was that you could have
a sort of view of systems thinking and
economic change and political change on
the one hand and you also had people
talking about personal transformation
and spiritual growth on the other and
they were not very often talking to each
other there were communities where they
were but even in those conversations it
wasn't clear how how productive and
creative the conversations were there
was a sense in which people had their
natural biases how do they want to speak
about all the things we should do to the
economic model or they were more
inclined to talk about stages of human
spiritual maturation and the kinds of
practices we should do to get there and
perspectiva was founded partly to make
sense of that connection and realize
it's a long-term conversation we call
ourselves an urgent 100 year project for
that reason because we recognize that
you know systems are complex and often
in any given case and you have multiple
systems interlocking as we do at the
moment
but you also have the kind of interior
'ti of the systems and so when you bring
all those things together you get a very
deliciously complex but often hard to
communicate set of insights and ideas
and there are there aren't that many
people who can sort of play at that
level if you like but it's uh certainly
one of them Zachary Stein whom we asked
thought to write for us as well as
another and they appear on the emerge
website because Amer
as part of perspectiva we were part of
the creation of it and over time we've
taken more more responsibility towards
it in due course the distinction is
basically they emerge is meant to be
relatively accessible emerges is
designed to be reaching a large audience
whereas perspective is maybe a little
bit more challenging precise
intellectually exacting and so the in
ideal world we get these pieces pitch to
refined and edited so they can reach
many people but then we could talk
further as we are here and get drill
down a little bit more depth and clarity
about what's being said right because
one of the things that Bonita mentions I
think often is the danger of let's say
very reductive thinking and I guess the
danger of manifesto in a sense and I'm
calling it that you didn't call it that
but it does have a let's say a vision to
it one of the dangers is is this kind of
reductionism so I wonder if we're living
in a time where you know there is the
danger of a very very quick quick we're
living in a time that's very urgent on
one hand and an end at a time that
requires very careful careful thought at
the other and maybe that's the that's
the line or that's the attention yeah so
I want to call it a halt a pesto so it
looks like a manifesto but it has a
holistic kind of view instead of a
reductive view so if you want to keep
calling it something we can go out a
hole of Festo so here's where we need to
be careful there is reductionism that's
like scientific reductionism so we
abstract from experience down to
concepts and then we can manipulate the
concepts as if they stand in for the
whole that's one thing now the
postmodern systemic mind moves away from
that kind of reductionism toward what we
would call synthetic systems making so
larger and larger systems more and more
points to contextualise you know
transdisciplinary kind of integrations
and syntheses and these build hyper
objects right so it's not reductionist
but it has its own liability there's no
there's no pivot point in which to act
you can't get in there okay that's what
I wanted to actually bring up as like
you mentioned in your email that you
wanted this stuff to be actionable hmm
yeah so then what's the Third Way right
if we don't want to build hyper objects
and and I'm not saying all the first two
are not necessary I'm saying that they
each give us valuable insight into what
we're dealing with but there's this
third way and this Third Way has is it's
a move into the felt sense a move into
the body a move into like getting real
with what is your despair or what is
what is possible from here like what is
simply possible from here and as as
Jonathan knows I went through this
process with this article because first
it was big and synthetic and I hated it
because it was just a clever use of your
mind in a certain way hmm so what is
being asked of me what is being asked of
me at this point in history you know
what and from there and this article
emerges and so for example I'll just
give you how it's how it can play out
after I wrote the article I was in the
process of doing these community calls
with various different groups for a week
once a week for three weeks and in this
one group someone said Oh what I'm
working with so-and-so and we're
building blockchain technology
to recreate the whole US economy and you
know it's very bright person and then he
said but the problem of course is only
you know not even 20% of people will
actually get it they're too stupid and I
said we don't need sophisticated
financial instruments we need simple
financial instruments that everyone can
understand that guaranteed to work for
them you see the difference now it took
me a long time
actually not until I wrote this article
did even I get it because I was like
chasing like more and more complexity in
this and that and when I realized that
we could just have a simple funnier
everyone understands how to do this that
didn't have to take down the whole
economy I thought oh my god what if I
thought more like this maybe maybe
there's a lot hidden in plain sight a
lot of potential in plain sight but this
is a different kind of thinking and I
don't you know want to go meta on the
thinking one of your audience will
there's a whole nother you know PhD in
that but this is like for me what what
the invitation is that Jonathan is
looking for and like Zak does the same
he does a similar thing but you know
it's all orthogonal to like he said I
think on your video
I didn't even propose anything you know
I wasn't even arguing for anything he he
he took something from insider and
himself and put it in the context of
this and so this is I think what
Jonathan has it's a nose for but you
know anyway something like imaginal is
the word that comes to mind or or this a
word I got from from John Verve a key he
talks the difference between imagination
just imagining all these things and kind
of going into a fantasy of how the world
could be where as actual concrete
imaginal I think that's what Zak was
doing he was putting forth imaginal
structures that we could work with
rather than let's say a research paper
more
something like that did you want to
respond Jonathan yeah sure so there's a
lot going on and it's fascinating to
hear the process angle on what's being
said before we get delving into material
of it the substance of it um I've been
going through a little bit of a trip
myself for the last few weeks because
I've been countered partly through
Benitez SC we should use the word origin
arey mmm the use this word origin arey I
thought she'd be the type of right which
is it which is kind of embarrassing but
an embarrassment and happy tune up see
and ordinary is actually a term from
jean gebser and it's a really important
notion and it's usefully juxtaposed with
imaginary and you've mentioned the
imaginal and Rousseau to sort of frame
these different notions the imaginary is
often this sort of the kind of like the
inside of the whole world
the imaginary is something like how we
experience culture writ large and how it
circumscribes our notion of what's
normal the imaginary is that which is
it's several layers of abstraction
beyond you know your immediate
experience than your culture it's kind
of a holding pattern for a subjective an
interest subjective experience and there
are ways of describing I think Charles
Taylor calls it the widest possible
grasp of our whole predicament right so
that's a nice area a lot of people have
been speaking recently about the need
for a new social imaginary because their
master we have is basically as a
consumerist late capitalist world
falling apart imaginary and maybe we can
be better and that's one of the ideas
out there but with the richer deeper
perhaps more profound notion which is
connected with the evolution of
consciousness which is sort of saying
look these imaginaries will either be
given unto us by processes of history
mostly material processes like what's
happening to land what's happening with
technology what's happening with
population movements we will give rise
to subjective an interest subjective
experience right and that keeps on
happening until we get to a point now
where something you become aware hang on
we're calling this thing called the
imaginary what's going on
can we change it are we are we subject
to it is there a sense in which we can
build our own imaginary that's a highly
non-trivial process because it's like
you know a spiderweb being reconstructed
after it's broken up broken down your
your your coming out of something kind
of natural and process-driven
and cleaning that you can through a sort
of effort who will recreates it and it's
highly questionable that we can which is
where the idea of the origin area
becomes interesting because in effect
you're saying look look more deeply at
those processes follow them back to
where they started look at the origin
right and this is where again steep
which is you know what kind of origin
well mathematical origin certainly
mathematical becoming physical becoming
chemical becoming biological becoming
evolution becoming psychological
becoming spiritual but arguably right at
the beginning it was numinous yeah this
is since our theological water but the
whole idea of the origin the origin
living on captures famous pookas called
the ever-present origin I'm still
graphic again we don't wanna give any
sort of false authority here but but I'm
excited by his work because it tallies
with a lot of other thinkers mark Vernon
is also an Associated perspectiva is
ungrate work and bringing bringing new
and Barfield to public attention here is
something different about participator
annoying but as Bonnie I think was
alluding to earlier getting away from a
way of knowing that is sort of abstract
and sort of event mental models and
getting back into the world
rediscovering your original tacit
understanding of things and no longer in
a naive way recognizing that they're
situated within these cultural contexts
these are national contexts but no
longer being asked subject to them being
able to somehow get back to you know
it's like in the Zen tradition this
because before enlightenment carrying
water and chopping wood and after and
light carrying water chopping wood so
the origin Airy for me this notion is
quite a profound wise it's something
like saying there is a challenge with
our social imaginary for the essence of
the challenge is that we have to find a
way to rediscover the origin Airy the
sort of origin of this
of creation and recreation that we're
caught up in and I become conscious
agents of that in some way and how we
don't know but that's where we are I
think that's wonderful and before you
speak on that Bonita I remember in your
article you mentioned something about
how you compared sort of the project of
going to the moon right as this is
something that the American ego felt
like it needed to do to go to the moon
like land on the moon right to define
itself to be to be something whereas
whereas you were saying that our task
right now and this is just putting
simply what what Jonathan sakes is
saying about the originally this is just
step on the earth like that's the more
difficult task that we have to do does
that does that ring true is that is that
a good segue to what Jonathan was saying
yeah so you know I really I wasn't I
wasn't critiquing the moon shot yeah
sorry
Rick that was my critiques yeah yeah not
yours excuse me you know it's
interesting because I linked that speech
and many people emailed me and they were
blown away like there are young people
who never see leaders talk like that so
whether you think it you know whatever
your your retrospective historical
critique on those times is that's not
how it was playing out at the time so
yeah but now it's a different you know
it's it's a different need it's a
different calling it's a different
aspiration let's say it's you know and
for me like part of what I said in the
last part about digital naturalism is a
lot of for me a lot of is that a lot of
what we need to do is hidden in plain
sight but our way of thinking about
intelligence and development means that
everything
in the future and more complexity as
always his progress represents progress
this is not surprising because we live
in a competitive growth economy based on
information so we escalate the
complexity of information regardless of
whether it's in the right direction so
we don't really in general this is true
in organizations as well as individuals
in general we don't create organizations
that are committed to a task in the past
organizations would commit to a task
they built something and then they would
they would die out now we create
organizations that are committed to the
life lifelong profit of the organization
doesn't matter what the task is so very
few people get really clean on what's
the task what are we trying to do you
know killings and so the moonshot is
perfect
it's very clear we're going to the moon
all the learnings and all the other
things are inside that commitment in
that goal so and so we need that kind of
you're saying we need that kind of
direction that kind of intense you know
direction even that that sounds like a
grand narrative that we need though you
know going to the moon is a big project
right so I'm just saying there's kind of
a a paradox and what you're saying is
that we don't we don't want to be too
grandiose about about our project but it
has to be a grand project so I have a
thought yeah I make it reminds me pretty
much distinction by the the teachers at
the Harvard Kennedy School called long
high fights and these things things
between technical problems and adaptive
problems or technical challenges and
adaptive challenges through precise
and he says that so much of leadership
makes the mistake of treating adaptive
challenges as technical problems but
most leadership errors stem from that
mistake and I know this would not apply
to Bonnie but it's an interesting
juxtaposition when you think of the
moonshot it's true that that rallied a
lot of attention and imagination and
excitement the earth became somehow
object rather than subject because we
can escape from it and then we can look
down on it and see how beautiful it was
and that's a huge achievement so it's
not simply technical but it's also true
that the problem of how to get to the
moon is technical in nature where is the
problem of how do you design governance
structures and viable economies for a
roughly eight billion people on
ecologically compromised and
technologically imperious world that's
not a technical problem that's an
adaptive challenge at scale and so while
we do need a new moonshot in spirit
there will have to be a very different
kind of endeavor it's an endeavor in
which were thoroughly implicated not as
bystanders but as participants so maybe
you could speak to that Bonnie yeah so
principles and what act what should we
do again as you say you wanted this to
be very yeah so people are always
there's have been a lot of talk a lot of
podcasts yeah what sound the actions be
sorry yeah no I think that that was
beautiful so I completely agree with
what Jonathan said and I'm actually
learning and really rich perspectives on
this so I'm gonna call it one-stop
shopping you see the the way the
difference between the moonshot and the
way we're working now is the way we're
working now is very fractionalized right
so this group this group of the voting
population what's free education this
group wants this this group so in fact
this group wants that and so it's all
there's no one that holds a vision
there's no there's no so the moonshot
created alignment it created new
economic opportunity it created the lead
for a lot of growth in the computers you
know computer sector with
was starting up not really didn't really
have a challenge it created this
rearranged the Geo social world big time
it created the opportunity for GPS all
these things it also created a great
opportunity for women at the time which
is underreported so it's like one-stop
shopping what is a moonshot that
naturally aggregates or creates holistic
interdependencies so you get more you
know more bang for your buck so it's to
me that was like so what are the what
are the I think I started with 12 some
of them were unfolded and others what
are the what could be something like
that and so that's how we come with the
SIP so for example if you and I try to
take things that were doable and
emerging already so the notion of a
citizen's currency is very very much
embedded in a lot of work that people
are doing with digital currency but also
with PayPal I mean when PayPal came
online it was extraordinary because up
until then the sec the Security and
Exchange Committee would have shut them
down without a doubt because you
couldn't build your own kind of currency
thing he wasn't a bank per se these
imaginaries these these these you know
expansion of our economic imagination
there's lots in the system already but
as I said earlier it's like what is the
easiest one what is the low-hanging
fruit that we could just do today now
coronavirus has given us an opportunity
to remind people that they're interested
now in their food chain and it'd be easy
in fact some of us have been researching
apps this really cool apps to find you
know to watch your food chain and have
that currency the
off the value-added investment interest
currency and that would be ubi would be
a better type a ubi
because it would not be subject to the
extractive financial instruments in the
main economy so can we just move the
needle there now all of a sudden what
happens a lot happens if you could get
your let's say health care and food from
this currency and let's say you keep
rent in housing and mortgages on the
other currency and then your and then
your landlord tells you to you know you
can't pay your rent your landlord says
get out or don't pay your rent get out
will you said well I'll get out like
you're so much more fluid now so the
rental charge to all the all the
pressure will now be on renters they
would be competing with themselves and
there's a lot of young people who like
to go back into rural areas and build
farms but they can't because you'll
starve to death basically it takes like
ten years but if you had your health
care and your food paid for then you'd
get rural revitalization if you add this
local currency for health care you could
get a lot of more health care services
like like they do in I think Amsterdam
there's something that's it's not
Morningstar but where you have local
knowledge for certain kind of health
care outside of the insurance system
like you know chiropractic started that
way
homeopathic started that way I when I
got it so so just to show you how how
big a deal this is when I left my job
and lost my health care I got a very bad
injury in my arm I needed like 120
internal stitches and 80 external
stitches antibiotics and an x-ray but I
didn't have health and
I didn't I didn't get a surgeon I got a
medical technician who done two tours in
Iraq he did a beautiful job and it cost
me $1,900 that's it that's the true cost
of health care a certain amount of
artisan vocational knowledge and X
amount of hours in us you know in a room
in an office so but this won't have this
can't happen when it's run on the
extractive system because you get you
know you get the taxes you get the
interest you get the loans you get the
insurance companies all of this inflates
the cost of health insurance so our
government for example in the u.s. we
want universal health care but we're not
going to pay the health care workers
we're going to pay the insurance so your
versal health care under the existing
system means universal raping of your
labor into insurance profits so that
just one move can start to peel away it
really incentivizes just natural human
activity in the way we want so that's
why it's not just all of these I think
are multiple have multiple leverages
leverage points and support each other
so maybe if we could just do the other
ones in a little bit yeah that's great
um so so basically once people have a
baseline of survival uh-huh without the
fear of you know being hungry and if we
diversified the if we diversified money
so that our value or into something
called the citizens currency then you
you were suggesting that the both both
systems like we would have different
systems of money different kinds of
currencies of systems and that would
that would this diversification would
allow us to be more natural in our and
our activities
I think the diversification itself would
enable us to take a look at the the the
extractive economy that we have the
central banking economy yeah and so I
wouldn't so that's also another
advantage do this
and now you can see do we need this and
maybe there are advantages you know
gifts so it's like it's different then
becoming more and more complex in trying
to see how I'm gonna solve everything at
once it's like this is doable it's right
in front of our face I even talked about
like people having reports quarterly
reports of where the money's going
farmers needed it here we these farmers
didn't need it you know you could start
to see currency as this network effect
mmm so I I see promise on that idea but
I also see lots of potential qualms and
I'm sure Bonnie herself you know where
someone else to propose these ideas she
would be quick to see that there are
perspectives that need to be brought to
bear you know for example it's just
happening in one country alone and if it
is that creates certain even greater
immigration pressures on that country
it also will it will impact on you know
is it okay for the central government to
allow it affect multiple money supplies
what will that mean for things like
inflation and interest rates on
mortgages and so forth um I'm not sort
of bonafide the economists that I've
spent enough time reading economics
books but I know that there are are
economists who would be interested
you're interesting to ask about these
things this is quite an interesting
conversation in the sense that it caught
economics is too important to be left to
just the economists on the one hand but
it's also true that once you get an idea
like here's an app for a new idea of a
currency and we can tailor make it to
parts and some parts of the economy
which are essential and keep it out of
the parts of the economy which are about
revenue extraction and
interest and debt and all the rest of it
now I think maybe I'm I'm very open to
it but I'm also keen to stress that we
don't really know so this is the
difference between bonny having an
interesting idea and let's explore it
let's see what it looks like and that's
very differently saying here's a
solution
it's much more about saying here's a
different way of thinking about money
and technology and human need and their
magnificent
combination let's look into why we don't
do that and whether we can actually
build it ourselves
but equally while you're doing that you
might find there some killer a
counter-argument to say sorry you just
can't do that I don't know what it is
I'm just saying we should be open to
that no I agree and I think the call
really the next step call is can we
start communities of practices that are
working aligned in in this one or
something like this I don't and but so
this is that so but I really like the
fact that these questions are asked
immediately so I call it a citizen's
currency because when I work it out it
the first step has to be bounded by the
nation-state it gets crazy so I've
worked that out so I call her citizens
currency so it would be limited at first
because then there would have to be some
changes but the demand inside the nation
would would cause smart changes so
that's that's clear and then there would
have to be certain subsidies and trade
agreements that that enable the
countries that want to try this to do
this without disrupting everything so
that's why it's called a citizen's
currency and for those people working on
blockchain etc it's actually a
suggestion that they work at that scale
and not at the scale be internet for
example which most people are working so
this is an interesting thing it's less
disruptive also in terms of immigration
I've been thinking about it as a natural
instrument to preserve and improve the
immigration flows of farmworkers so it
doesn't solve all of immigration
obviously but
these are ways in which you can take one
simple idea and start to weave in some
things like you just discussed that are
important but I do see it as bounded
unless somebody can think outside the
box I just see that it would require but
then there's that that there there's the
interest in having a little more kind of
kind of stepping back to a little more
sense of nationhood already so some of
these things might be it might be timely
right I mean for my part I don't doubt
that some version of a citizen's
currency and the citizen you know could
be citizens of the world potentially but
I can see why there would be good design
reasons for beginning more locally and I
also can hear people who are outraged
because somehow for them it's almost a
sacred notion that one works for one's
own key and then I can see the critiques
of that saying well that's all very well
in principle but we live in being
thoroughly interconnected highly
urbanised worlds where it's just not
that easy and often you starve if you
try yeah so it's a it's a complex pitch
right I suppose my question back to you
is when we come up with an idea like
this or a variation of it and
simultaneously you have other ideas that
you have in your list and we know there
are plenty of other ideas out there
there's a question of orientation like
where do you start the thinking process
and because one of the things that's
been interesting about Col vid and the
pandemic is some people have begun to
realize okay where do we start so I
noticed for example the in in ethical
Theory there are sort of main schools of
with a canteen or the ontological view
that certain things are better than
enough themselves so saving life is a
kind of preeminent necessity but then
you have a more consequential view which
is something like well and we can't save
all the lines and and if we do try and
save all the lines then we'll damages a
lot of things and so we've let's through
the trade-offs and that's another way of
thinking then you have something like
virtue theory which is more about one of
the inherent qualities of human
character that we need to cultivate at
this moment here and kind
reciprocity and things like this now
those things are all swirling around and
I noticed in my own reaction that my
inner cancion became sort of heightened
when the pandemic broke I was thinking
first save all the lights so that was my
very strong primal instinct like just
keep people inside figure out what's
going on and let's see like but let's at
least now that we understand you know
what exponential exponential functions
look like you can see that this could
kill a lot of people very fast and every
bit counts and therefore begin I took my
my children out of school early against
government advice because I sense this
basically my my sense was first save all
the lives right I only mention that
because in their more broader sense when
you're thinking of redesigning society
or the economy and a potentially global
scale and you may have to start locally
because as you said Andrea and as
Bonnie's emphasizing it's all very well
to have transcendental design but you've
got to do something the next day and we
need to start somewhere too so there's
this trade-off between knowing that the
context is plural and planetary but
recognizing that action is often
personal and specific and local and and
in that context what are the load stars
are in touch tones well health is
certainly one of them you know what does
it mean to design an economy that's
about health broadly conceived I know
there are people who are thinking about
that Nora Bates since one of them and
there's also the question of education
because it is AK is that argument is
compelling peace there's a lot going on
educationally at the moment you know
it's not just that kids are not in
school I know as a parent I'm having to
teach myself how to be a functional
intermediary between the schools demands
and the child's capabilities and desires
and that's not easy it's a steep
learning curve for all of us and then
there's a bigger question of you know
learning as a as a species wide
challenge to make sense of civilization
and its purposes and for that you've got
to think well if it's not indefinite
indefinite economic growth if we're not
just trying to get richer and assuming
it will somehow trickle
what are we doing and that's where I'm
curious to ask Bonnie about the list
because it's like okay I can see that
these are all interesting things to do
what is their underlying dynamic what
are they are they are they aimed of the
increase of love or well-being or what
is it you know what you know how do you
orient yourself in that regard yes so a
couple of comments I hope I remember
them all excellent questions so the
first one is yes save all the lives
what's the trade-off that we're faced
with those say save all the lives or
ruin the economy I mean does does that
something I aspirational how about save
all the lives or build the world we want
to see ah now becomes very interesting
now there's you know you move from
content to some posing like carica
Guardian yeah yeah so so the notion of
saving lives then becomes at once maybe
more transcendent don't put more
primitive right you know people will
yeah so so but that we don't have that
right we don't have that save the lives
or you know save the economy and but we
do have it's a live save the economy or
take the saving of the lives response to
look at something new this is actually
the third wave that's been coming out in
this thing you know I'm sure that that's
not what people really wanted to do so
so that's that's one thing the other
thing is that you asked about healthcare
and this is why you know the the
interactive dynamics as the six are
important because you what health care
depends a lot of time education I think
we should teach you know we'll if you
live on a farm and you have a vet that
you like and you have a lot of animals
you basically do a lot of health care
yourself like a lot that you know
it's not that hard but most people don't
know anything about their bodies or the
immune system or you can't even google
and understand anything they don't know
how to take care of themselves and I eat
all of this inflates you know this big
systemic need for this big behemoth type
of health care this is true in all
Western cultures it's beginning to be
more true in the Eastern cultures so if
you have more education around health
care then you could have more
distributed nodes for carrying and so
that's one thing and I'll get back to
education but the connection piece
really helps health care because the
problem is we're not connected to how we
are human how our health is part of the
living world we're not we don't we're
not connected to with you know how we do
our forestry is part of our healthcare
system you know how we what the
decisions we make on land use is part of
our healthcare system
decisions we make in animal husbandry
which is why we have swine flu avian flu
and coronavirus is part of our health
insurance healthcare so we need to
cultivate this sense of origin Airy
connection that itself solves a lot you
know we're not even connected to our
bodies you know like the comorbidities
around diabetes and and and covered 19
are huge right so and diabetes is much
more is a much larger and more dangerous
pandemic because the young kids I mean
it's just infecting all the global for
long term so so it's it's it's so that
so the connection piece works with the
educate health care education with
health care but you also said you know
I'm not into giving people young people
basic income and free free college and
so part of the education piece which I
know is a very big piece because you and
I are working on it
is to have work-study college credits so
that just like you know the GI Bill and
you and those credits would come from
working in education healthcare
environment things like hospice and farm
and food so they have this like perfect
circle and so then when people go to
college and it this is proven to be true
they're more respectful they're more
informed of what what college means or
what college can be and so I would I
would stop says here go
I'll never run for office in this
country I would stop subsidizing all
higher education and and use use that
subsidy and let people who have the
money go
because basically let them go and try to
preserve the world that makes them rich
that's what education does it teaches
you how to preserve the world for rich
people I would use that money instead to
to design these work these I think it
starts in my my my project it starts
from 16 to 18 years old you start to
have a vocational support for working in
the society and then you can get work
credits for going to higher education
whatever that may look like at that time
so a lot of this stuff is like if if we
had enough conversations you could see
they're all deeply embedded in each
other I'm absolutely sure that having
not just having read it but know your
other work you know just knowing of the
kinds of countries I guess I'm just
curious about when I got my original
question why this list not known
otherwise you know there are lots of
books out there with it with in effect
10-point plans for how civilization
renews itself and many of them are a
little bit open-ended but they're still
like that and in all cases that have two
main qualms one is there's something
about the planning nature of it that
troubles me is that it's insufficiently
receptive the what might come being
sufficiently
curious about almost you know that joke
about man
man plans God laughs you know that sort
of thing is it's as if like is if we
could figure it out when there's so much
that's beyond our control um but there's
also this issue of underlying underlying
value a kind of that was a sort of meta
meta ethics in a way sort of thinking
about what what are the real ultimate
values that are driving the endeavor so
I don't die that the six point she
raised could spin us towards or what
would the right metaphor be it would
move us towards or some ball yeah tumble
to Wars yeah something on that playfully
fold on the hill towards whatever and
basically I agree that could be the case
but I'm curious in order to make
decisions do we or do we not need some
kind of underlying commitment to certain
core virtues or processes of
understanding where its shoes or you
know whatever that is is there not some
one aspect or am I looking for something
that just isn't there
no no so can I say can I just make one
thing when you're talking what I'm
hearing Jonathan say maybe is that we
need a metaphysical system as well as
just this idea of changing stuff like
like a religion or something you know a
religion is a metaphysical system that
sort of keeps the society together and
is that fair just to quickly spin on
that before when it comes in and yes
metaphysics I nobody's written about
that so it's an interesting chance for
her to go into that it's not just
metaphysics though so it is something
about ultimate commitments
I suppose it's also about the the
rhetorical function of the plan
something about making sense the people
of why we should do X and not Y by
appealing to Zed um so meaning right
meaning what's the meaning of what we're
doing
the point is you see meaning someone
else's happiness someone else's justice
someone else's diversity some
Elsie's hell I don't want to know of how
you're gonna deal with that or are you
just gonna say everyone's welcome we can
do together and bring all your values
with you like hi reet so how do we solve
that conundrum in a busy Taoist way
maybe yes the thing is designed to solve
itself so I just step back know and
that's kind of a joke okay so here are
different ways to look at it one is it's
informed by a lot of key features of my
work right release complexity
self-organization it's it's designed so
if people buy in then you really have a
lot of experiments going on it's not a
top-down thing this notion of releasing
complexity this notion of the different
type of meta move it is and the fact
that it like literally almost killed me
to write it like what do you want to say
but so maybe it's only authentic though
one person that but all these things
depend upon timing you know like is
there sufficient that is this speaking
to other people what they can't get out
of themselves you know and I had a
community call the other day and people
like there's a lot of people close to
saying certain similar things but they
don't say it in public because it seems
like retro Romanticism you ask that
question it has all these maybe they're
not I get away with it because I've been
like writing complex metaphysics so
people think well she must be smart
I mean basically that's one of the
reasons why people like Zack and I get
away first with saying these things
because we had to prove that yes all of
that and yet there's something else
right so that's part of it and the
question is like Wilbur I mean Wilbur's
work was great but it was also timely
he didn't say so anything that wasn't
said in little places elsewhere yeah but
he represents through the same process
and I don't think I don't know if this
is gonna be a big deal or not but it's
one of those things for me that's one
thing but the other thing you're talking
about is yes because you're so astute
there are underneath it
you could say what are the as I said in
my spirituality we need one of the
ontological epistemological and
metaphysical and Axia logical
commitments that we need today and I
think you can see from that short video
I did that that is what underlies this
but of course that's all I can say so
that's why I know there's also this
deeper holism it's me trying to come to
terms with Who am I at this time in
history as a person given all the work
I've done and can that be helpful this
is interesting to me like it seems like
rather than a bunch of commandments like
that you're talking about commitments
that we should make that are based in
this moment of time is that is that my
understanding you which might which is
that's a different thing than saying we
should always you know thou shalt not
kill or you know it's it's more like
okay it right now we're not gonna build
a thing to go to the moon right that's
inappropriate in this time maybe the
whole discussion about going to Mars
feels to me kind of inappropriate when
wildfires are burning in you know in
Australia so so yeah so what are what
are those what do you think I mean the
first thing is to realize you have them
and then you say wow these good these
actually a lot of people have
commitments that are not in the
direction of the values they espouse and
that's why they never get anything done
so I have watched the video Bonita
alluded to have also seen the text
because I edited well very lightly and
it's great other words which will go
online shortly actually but what she's
alluding to is a series by Bruce
alderman about the spirituality of
tomorrow or or the one we need today or
respectively the same thing in some ways
and and it was a particularly cogent
piece where Bonnie does kind of lay out
her metaphysics of choice and they
include commitments to axiology which is
roughly the
structure of value or underlying
premises of value and goodness and so
forth and mr. Balaji which is about how
do we know and how should we know
ontology roughly what is real what is
the world made of and what do we know to
be real what is there and then also your
fourth process metaphysics which is in
some ways what I wanted to get to yeah
so think about a process metaphysics
that's very relevant in regard to my
aunt my question is that it's inherently
somewhat content and provisional right
it's inherently
no Kantian right it's creative minute to
process metaphysics then giving any
given list is a way of saying this is
where we are in the process at the
moment right the list is a way of the
process unfolding and speaking and you
you know answer the question of why
these points and that other is you can
give more or less good cartographical
references say well I actually touched
all the four quadrants of Wilbur's math
and this is a little bit a purse per
table and captures theory and it's this
and that you can do that and your your
list may look more or less credible as a
result I suppose the thing I'm trying to
get to is is that enough is that as much
as we can do and if so let's just get on
with it or is it more is it that there's
another way of doing this such that you
bring together the best and the
brightest as it were bringing all the
lists happy everyone has their ten-point
plan and there's a thousand of them and
then you Whittle that down to one
ten-point plan at the end because that's
the one that survived that doesn't seem
right that seems bogus right and and and
I'm wondering the reason it seems bogus
is something about the nature of in your
model knowing valuing being and what
holds all of that is is radically
respectable in other words it's it
depends upon the context and the person
it's not true for everyone and always
necessarily and therefore all you can do
is say this is what I think we should do
next
given our best available knowledge and
judgment and if that's the case you know
good luck but that's maybe that's maybe
that's all there it is yeah and I also
tried to highlight what's what's what's
possible okay there's a lot going on
it's always like playing a fairly
extraordinarily rich chess game with
Jonathan yeah cuz cuz every new move is
so many more possibilities you know
although it doesn't have this
competitive feel to it so good I could I
may throw in one little thing when I say
when you're talking about process
philosophy it seems to be a kind of a
creative process of unknowing and then
wait and then the and then there is also
maybe the need for metaphysical
certainty of some kinds on the other
side right like you don't do any harm
right that might be a kind of a
universal Kantian category so I'm almost
feeling like I'm almost feeling these
the two worlds let's say a Buddhistic
world or eastern taoist world and Ana
and Ana County and Christian world view
being being sort of compared to each
other yeah and I want to say to all my
dallas friends I mean I call myself a
Taoist but I've obviously upgraded what
that I think that means to me I mean
some doll is so very you know that
there's all kinds of Dallas but a lot of
commonalities so but but what I think is
interesting I think any list would be
fine it doesn't matter
you know maybe exactly how you do the
steps but these features that it
releases complexity doesn't use them it
you know medicine thetic mind that it it
arises from you know some deep inner
some sensing and
and that means you're it's going to be
back by these other commitments deep
inner sensing is your kind of tracking
through some kind of set of commitments
so you have to know what those
commitments are if that could be
explicated also I try to work you know
to release complexity I tried to work
with things that are already underway
you know the one that's the most
emergent is digital naturalism but I
tried to also ask the coronavirus like
what what are you telling us you know so
that's the the food to farm thing and
the way people are working and with
making bread and like the other day I
saw this guy who generally sells eggs to
restaurants had to was was going to have
to call his flock and he went straight
to Facebook and they he sells like two
months of eggs over Facebook this is the
move like you just go directly and now
that the system has to breathe food here
then it has to move food here this is
the move I try to work within the
intelligence and pro-social impulses of
human I try so there's certain kinds of
things if somebody else can if they have
these deeper touch points so maybe it
could be any other list but but I don't
think there's a whole if you had all
those touch points I don't think there's
a whole lot of yeah I wanted to ask you
about like hyper objects to the word
hyper object and it seems I don't know
if I understand what that means exactly
maybe people could benefit from
understanding that but I wonder if
removing the hyper object to have a more
direct relationship with with the world
is a bit what you're talking about is
that um I can just briefly speak to that
I know you're asking Bonnie but there's
a reason I wanted to come in which was
that I think this is one of the more
exciting features of bonitas thought
because I spend a lot of time with
people who think about the collapse of
civilization and the design
anyone you know gain be is is a complex
nested notion but a lot of people in
that world I'll do think in terms of
something like a transcendental design
in which you think it all through and
map out what this world would be like
with different underlying principles
different motivations different
incentive structures different
technologies different feedback loops
and so it goes on and whenever I hear
those things they don't feel all
together real and it's not because I
don't think we need that kind of
thinking it's because there's something
about the getting from here to there
that it's sort of ignored as if somehow
the process of getting from A to B was
not itself part of the story rather than
just what's a and what's B and so this
idea of working with what's already
there and sort of bill very very
important yeah yeah it's very important
so when we need to asks it's worth
noticing you know what does the
coronavirus saying to us it's it's a
very interesting way of posing the
question I feel it to be profoundly
ethical but not moralistic like we're
looking at the complex situation we're
not we're not imposing a sort of
moralistic map of or even let's say
trying to engineer this you know this
utopian society we're trying to really
work with the forces that are moving
through us and our communities and and
whatever happens to appear which might
be coronavirus right now yeah no I I
that's right I want to hear what bunny
wants to say about hyper objects but I
also have something to add the only feel
in the last few days I've really made my
pizza like objects in a certain sense so
yeah so this is work I've been doing for
a long time is you know Jonathan and
that is I've for a long time believed
that the complexity in human
consciousness as measured by
hierarchical developmental stage theory
is a product of adapting to an
information economy in a capitalist
society now actually the early Daoists
talked about this in terms of ethics
they said
now they'll have print their principles
don't touch any your brother's wife and
then they'll say well what if she falls
in the water they then they have context
but they when they argued with the mo s
they said you don't want to have more
and more complex rules because then
you'll only have you have to pay a few
people you don't know what they're
talking about and the average person
cannot make a moral decision so they
predicted that the the way complex
thinking works in the moral sphere is
highly problematic so now with this is
not about that but but what I would say
is that here's the challenge to smart
people today the challenge is not to
design double and triple loop systems is
to design single loop feedback systems
that work they're inherently inclusive
of everyone including young people and
that's what I'm doing
everyone knows how to use currency this
move to making systems more more and
more complex is inherently a rivalry
smooth and a capitalist information
economy now you don't have to buy into
that it's highly provocative I happen to
believe it and some people are studying
to also come around to it
Roy - star for example this was his
critique of the Texas well-versed
taxonomy so that's that so this moving
and hyper objects is is that move just
taking things and making them more and
more complex in a hierarchical
complexity that money can I come in
there because two things there one is
and not to hear more about what what
exactly you mean that is you seem to be
saying that they developed the impulse
to understand cognitive complexity
through developments or models is
somehow beholden to the capital
informational infrastructure and
therefore know exactly beholdin but it's
sort of shaped by it and serves it in a
certain sense I would put a little
cleaner than that developmental stage
models correctly reflect what's
happening
but that's not because our mind is like
that that's because it's a mind that's
developed in a rival risk okay yes so
they're there it's called the empirical
fallacy but they got evidence that
that's happening but they act as if this
is a deep structure of their mind I see
okay brilliant so it's not so in some
ways you could say it's a piston ology
claiming to be ontology something like
that yes right okay got it right so the
next question was about high progress
because only recently I feel I read
Timothy Morton's being ecological some
time ago I've spoken to here my trusted
intellectual friends about the nature of
hyper objects and it took me a while I
like you originally saw this as
primarily hyper abstract way of framing
things almost putting beyond the reach
or under collective understanding but
there's a more generous way to view more
- and I got through this through Jean
Johnson and his work on gebser but also
more generally thinking about what Zacks
been saying about and keeps saying that
the intellectual function is is is sort
of defeated by the hyper objects but
maddy means we can't the pandemic at
scale is beyond any single mind to
understand climate change of scale is
beyond any single mind even the notions
of inequality or democracy or these are
all examples of hyper object they tend
to have this function of being
simultaneously present and absent so
source or diffuse and their influence
and reference and yet simultaneously
present and real such that we refer to
them and they're part of our experience
but we can't pin them down they're not
tangible and now the more generous we
review hyper objects comes about through
a sort of going beyond perspectival
thinking so going beyond the lists going
beyond the conceptual categories
going beyond the taxonomy and the
blueprints and the games here at
theoretic understandings and saying no
just grinding in your own experience the
hyper organs our way of saying youth
that function has limitations it's not
saying here is the
theosis of the intellect itse intellect
must surrender that's why we have
archetypes and symbols and stuff too
right so it's just sort of an uber
archetype a big big well yeah I
understand it this is why you deciding
and Bonnie can correct me on this but as
I understand that one of the reasons
people that gets further exciting is
precisely because those ways of thinking
the more magic mythic kind of
perspectives are coming back people are
reaching for them and and feeling more
attune to them and that's partly because
they're more mental structures that
we've been living with predominantly for
the last decades and centuries are
losing their preeminence they're still
there we still need them you don't throw
your intellect I lightly you sort of
need it but there are other things going
on one of the things that's going on is
this kind of a purse for table view
which is a weight which is not a way of
saying you don't take perspective or you
don't have concepts but it's sort of
recognizing that you can experience the
whole thing and not be able to explain
it conceptually and that's partly what's
going on with with the covert 19 crisis
of endemic but also the bigger issues
like climate change people speaking
about the meta crisis what they're
alluding to is the ineffable wholeness
of our existential predicament expressed
in systemic terms that are beyond my
understanding and that's where hyper
objects are a bit more like your friend
you know they're a bit more like okay I
see why I can't get that it's a hyper
object and that's okay because there's a
limit to what I can understand because
I'm a single human being with epistemic
limitations that's how I see it so it's
a necessary kind of short form for
communication between peak between
people to understand things that are
that are beyond our understanding
come on I'll let Bonnie come in now I
mean I think that just like all these
new waves of understanding they they
morph and they get popularized and I'm
mostly critiquing the popularized
version when I teach Timothy Moore and I
always teach hyper objects in
conjunction to his other book
which I can't remember what the title of
it is but the subtitle is is something
about you know really having
relationships with the non-moving world
is a type of neo animism and I think the
two have to go hand-in-hand and the
second version is is usually much more
foreign to people that objects are part
you can participate with objects they're
non-trivial I like to say for example
that coffee moves billion people every
morning and I don't mean it in a trivial
way this is if you investigate you you
know what catalyzes your actions and
mate in many cases it's there they're
what we would call objects
so this those two pieces have to come
together for me in understanding Timothy
Morton but yes if you look at the
different ways to understand hyper
objects I agree with you yeah so maybe
you know this could that could be a list
of six things we should sort of do is
that they're there somewhere straddle
between the perspectival in the ape
respect idol they're sort of as a bridge
from one to the other so you want where
you want to get to are these tacit
understandings based on embeddedness in
relationship right but to get there you
need to build this sort of quasi
conceptual bridge that has practice
built into it so that we don't we know
where we're going to some extent yeah
and it has to have you know it has to be
anchored in the real dynamics of the
real world like is it possible to have a
currency like that is it possible to
track its food chain you know these
things are possible what I wanted to ask
you Bonnie about that it's okay with
Andrew is that you know the other
critique they become one is the sort of
a statistical romanticism the other
critique that I didn't mention that I
couldn't iron is how much you're
assuming about human you will
how much we're assuming that our better
natures are latent waiting to come out
and just need the right systems and
structures to elicit them and the what
extent are we just morally compromised
and self-interested and we'll there will
always be a critical mass of people in
any given group who will seek to subvert
the Commons and subvert patterns of
collaboration for their own selfish
advantage I know that people like
manuals frankenburger is very clear that
this is one of the main problems what he
doesn't really trust in anything within
our current competitive system is that
as long as those people are there they
will ultimately destroy things for
everyone and so I suppose I'm just
curious to know where you are with that
because you something to speak as though
there is this better nature that's
universal but I'm just not sure that's
the case I would say that you have to
have an optimistic you have to be able
to imagine optimistically but not that
people are good so for example one of
the one of the one of the hopes in
something like this is oh I wanted to
just spring in you know wouldn't what
you're talking about
working with what we have you know
that's a big thing in Jake Snowden's
work of exaptation right and I think
that we should also work with what we
have in terms of people people are going
people are not so good or whatever what
I see though however is the biggest of
reality of the moral quandary we have as
people now is not that we're not good
intentioned it's that there's good
intentions funneled through perverse
incentives and and I think everything
like people like Kant that currency be
gamed I'm like yeah sure any currency
can be gained but there's there's a it
can if there's a lot less it can do
so you know you can't invest in you
can't stock pilot you kid
so you want a lot of little
transgressions this is one of the
problems with Bitcoin it's that I think
they're working on it with hollow chain
successfully because hollow chain has
different levels of permissions so it's
closed circles can be a lot more wiggle
room but in a lot of big Bitcoin bit
chains blockchain technology imagines a
transgressed with society which is like
a dead society you know I mean our
values and our ways of imagining
ourselves evolved and they always come
online they emerge as deviant form so
this is something to think about in
terms of going forward and there's also
something about you know if you start to
look at how nature is composed itself
right versus the systems that we make we
want to always make systems that you
know can't be gamed are systems that
whatever retreat a withdrawal but things
like cheating and parasitism all these
things are highly evolutionary in nature
and so that's again you know a lot a lot
of this conversation and and it's hard
for me to so I'm not saying not just
throwing stones here a lot of this
conversation is from the impression that
the system is big and you know system
number one the big we we can hardly use
that word and not think of nature as a
system it's so distributed we don't need
it's not even a system because it's so
open
yeah and so part of this work if people
wanted to work on this approach is
helping each other even understand what
we mean when we talk about that kind of
system yeah because it's not bounded
and you know so if I have a really good
series of articles and medium that
sounded self-promotional but it goes
through like the different levels of
system thinking zero level which is just
participation all the way and it shows
all the moves that are made by the mind
to increase the complexity of those
systems and so what you can do with that
that analysis is systematically work
back so for example at a certain level
of systems thinking you D animate some
part of the system and there's a there's
there's a liability to that so you know
I think that Nora Bateson you people in
our community Dave Snowden we're all
trying to figure out the language and
what is it to talk about this kind of
process or dynamics that it doesn't know
so that's kind of a challenge you said D
animating the system which I thought was
kind of interesting because in these
theoretical two worlds the problem with
the present world is there's a lot of
dead structures right that need to be
kind of animated that means it's kind of
fall apart before more positive
structures can emerge yeah what I meant
by that is like the original sin of the
ecological management movement we can
manage ecosystem so that we are active
and the ecosystems D animated and there
is this is one of the original
incentives of whole it would I call
holistic systems thinking it's kind of
control right yeah it's it's a mania for
controlling whatever it could come from
from good intentions but you notice you
say you know I'm subject your object to
that and whenever you do that then the
system is going to come back to bite you
right or management systems management
thinking
different theories of management show
how you can they envision the workers as
being agents but then the manager can
step outside and see it as a human
system and act on it right so now I have
a privileged position from which I can
act on the system well this is this is
not true in highly caught it's not true
of nature it's not true the coronavirus
this is exactly what the model mental
model is of coronavirus that we can act
on something that's not true you have to
take a different orientation and
understand that the orientation is is
really good work but that's just one
there's nine I think different features
of systems thinking they can move you to
this this other way of yeah being with
complexity oh yeah that makes the
question is like how do we act and with
what is our agency and all of these
things and and and part of that is I
guess activity and part of that is like
you're the Taoist King and you're just
facing south and that's how you roll
your kingdom not by by messing with
whatever's going on sorry Jonathan you
wanted to well just just to sort of that
cool I'm red bow nice piece on it sounds
fascinating on different ways of
understanding systems thinking but I am
aware of the fact that there's a lot of
talk of changing the system a lot of
times change and not that much
reflection on what we mean precisely by
system nor the scales that that applies
to micro macro so and everything else in
between and then the different kinds of
systems such that you know the sort of
self-organizing system that is the mind
is very very different from the kind
before system that is the virus and
again I like what you're saying it may
be it isn't even a system well the
ecosystem is not a system maybe well
but we were so used to thinking in those
terms but they're not exactly what I
think what I'm sort of maybe in a sense
pulling my punches a bit I just feel
systems systems thinking unless it's
given the kind of texture that when he's
disappointing to risk being Hollow
it risks being a kind of picking
something out of the social surround to
sign clever design insightful but actual
to really feel systems and to recognize
one's participation in them is it
altogether more and more exacting
challenging tasks because as Bonnie says
we are we have multiple systems inside
of us there is a sense in which we are
one system ourselves but then we're
embedded in many others so to even speak
of systems is to bring into the room
like thousands of layers of complexity
and ok there's no point in getting lost
in that you need to get back to and
therefore but just that we maybe need to
refine our conception of when we say
system I mean X just as when we sit in a
moment and we say when I say I mean this
version of it or when I say democracy I
mean this I mean the little demo
likewise the system changing the system
I've often thought was a bit bit hollow
and also it has a kind of ingratitude
for you know we've got to this point in
culture and we've been struggling with
it if you just want to change the system
there's this deep deep history that the
system is is is comes from right and you
know people that people have this
tendency to want to wipe everything away
in this sort of blank slate that's
that's I think the heart of the point me
turning through and there's a good
reason for that and that's what is
uniquely Benito's in some ways and for
me at least because I'm also resting
with that being in a communities where
the language is very much of things have
to die before they can be reborn
and we need to tear down capitalism and
we need and democracy is finished and
and none of this quite rings true and
yet it doesn't ring wholly false either
there is a sense in which the
interlocking pressures of multiple great
systemic breakdowns and their
relationship does mean we're
encountering something like existential
risks if not catastrophic risks and I
think that's kind of right but when it
comes to what to do we don't have the
option of starting from school ground
zero like it's just not there what we
have instead is our next move and chest
rooms now the position is what the
position is you the pieces are where the
pieces are you can play better or worse
but it's your move you know that's how I
see it
and yeah to make a good movie to think
ahead certainly I need to learn from
what you've done wrong in the past right
well don't think you can just wipe the
pieces away and start again you know you
it's not not how life is yeah and I
think that I love there's a lot you just
said there so I'm gonna pick out some
gems
oh so you said the mind is a
self-organizing adaptive you know
self-organizing system now the mind has
complex feed loops right so that some
some areas when they get excited inhibit
other areas and those may be inhibited
earlier so when they inhibit this you
know it's a very complex and so the
moves we make or the thoughts we have
our threshold events like literally if
I'm like should I go to the store not
both those are in me sub threshold at
the same time until what happens and the
reason why this is adaptive is the same
reason why when you're receiving a serve
even moving in the wrong direction is
better than standing still right look so
so now if you look at coronavirus and we
say what is the cell what is the self
organizing collective intelligence of
coronavirus well what you would want to
see is a lot of things going on all the
time the information ecology rich with
all
relatives until you have a threshold ago
and dog that's what we have so now the
sudden instead of like having a sense
making breakdown
you know the freaking war on sense
making you actually see the system is
doing what he needs to do in complex
environments now there's too much need
for people to want one answer and this
is where you destroy yourself so you can
start to see I call it there's a term I
use still hunting will you just you just
all the information ecology I don't know
what to make of it but it's changing the
way I I no longer feel like I'm lost
like it's this need to think well what
is the answer and if this then that is
more actually more confusing than
watching the self-organized
collective intelligence we need to make
that information ecology more robust but
when that when that New York doctor you
know New York knew that was coming their
way
and weaning he got out and said look I'm
a pulmonary surgeon or whatever a
respiratory expert he says I've never
seen something like this before this is
not pneumonia and he came on like you
too
and then scientists looked at all these
different studies and all these
different ways of experimenting with
respirators versus ventilators this was
in real time and this has never happened
before the professional career of the
doctor would have been at risk and all
this stuff so the same thing that you
can look as a breakdown in sense making
I see as emergent emergent ways of
working with complexity at that level
and you want to see these a lot of sub
thresholds experiments I think Sweden is
marvelous for doing their own experiment
you know geopolitically they're they're
able to get away with it but you can
start to see and then if you can start
to see you can it's already happening
let's do more of this and less of that
it's not entirely new actually I feel
quite good about about about this as a
kind of as a kind of sort of conclusion
because it makes me feel less
gloomy about humanity in terms of you
know it's self-organizing the potential
do you have something you want to add to
that Jonathan what what Bonita said um
well just just to sort of echo it really
I suppose I would have I would add just
this that it very much encapsulates how
I'm what I'm experiencing in my current
role which involves working with a lot
of people who are thinking at this level
of complexity at a time when people are
desperate for answers and there's also I
think a certain fetishization of
different types of critique which I'm a
little bit guilty of myself sometimes
the desire to solve a problem the desire
to see civilization wide phenomena as if
there were essentially problems that
could be solved rather than a kind of
predicament or pickle that we're all
caught up in together and that we have
to experience more deeply somewhere and
then find felicitous action find a way
of doing something meaningful and real
and useful but in a way that is not
anti-intellectual in a way that doesn't
say oh you and your funny ideas you know
I'm going to go be practical and do
something know these two things are
needed together we've never needed
praxis more and naive positivity we
don't need either in some ways the
predicament is objectively well its
subjectively dark but objectively quite
precarious you could say and yet the
cope arises from the action it's not
that you have to hope in a new Act it's
that you find something meaningful to do
begin doing it and you find what's
mobilize then there's all sorts of
interesting ideas on what to do next and
I think in that sense but Wieters really
helped with his su series because it
gives you an idea here's some things we
can build what's stopping us
and yeah the raquan Xand yes there are
questions about how and when and who but
the key thing is to begin something
where you have confidence and this is a
beneficial move yeah and not to wait for
the big master plan yeah I love the fact
that there's it's a kind of it's a kind
of not naive optimism in the sense is
just recognizing the resources that we
have that are already there it's an
authentic positivity I haven't called it
Shan Ferguson you with this term I find
it very useful it's the positivity on
the other side of the analysis of
negativity you know it's like what you
do when you face up to the problem but
still have to act it's not everything's
going to be okay it's not everything is
okay it's things are difficult now what
do we do yeah and like in wartime or
something there the even even in in
whatever the situation is it can be very
very dark and very very terrible there's
still there still there's still some
sparkling or of creativity happening at
the same time and and so there's this
double is this double-edged sword or a
double double two worlds again that are
that are happening simultaneously I
think right now which which bonita
expresses very well in your in her
vision we don't have to answer it now
but i mean one of the things I'm left
with never quite sure what we should
want at a civilization wide level you
know it's just not my if not someone
asked me to sketch utopia
I would really struggle you know there's
something and I say struggle a little
bit ironic I say that because in some
ways for me the struggle that we face
now is quite close to how I want to live
you know it's like having these big
conundrums to wrestle with and try and
act on is is in its own way beautiful
now it's not to say I wouldn't want
things more peaceful I don't want people
to be tortured or starve
I don't want delusional forms of wealth
that lead to others being destroyed
through poverty I
on ecological suicide you know there are
clear things that we can do that anyone
could the same person could agree on but
beyond that painting a picture of how
you want the ultimate world to be that's
beyond me I just don't I can't quite
conceive of a world of optimal conflict
in that way I I don't know if others can
I'm curious about that but I think what
I can relate to and what Bonita is
really helping is thinking about next
steps do you have anything that you
would like to close off with Bonita
anything that's hanging around and the
conversation that you would like to kind
of perhaps conclude mean I just really
appreciate that reflecting that what
Jonathan said and you know I would just
say it in a different way you know how
the world is is not up to us but how we
act in the world we have is is